Guide to the Eleanor Elliott Papers, 1768-2006 and undated, bulk 1951-2006 RL.00358
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Eleanor Elliott papers
1768-2006 and undated (bulk 1951-2006)
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Elliott, Eleanor, 1926-2006
RL.00358
55 Linear Feet
Eleanor "Elly" Elliott was a women's rights activist, a board member of NOW's Legal Defense and Education Fund, a Barnard College Board Member, served on the National Advisory Council on Women's Educational Programs and was an editor at Vogue magazine. These materials consist of personal papers from the Elliott family and administrative files from Elliott's work in various women's rights organizations and philanthropic activities. It also includes photographs, scrapbooks and some audio/visual materials.
40,500 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research with the exception of the Barnard College series, which is restricted until 2025.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the Rare Book, Manuscript, and Special Collections Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Eleanor Elliott Papers were received by the Rare Book, Manuscript, and Special Collections Library as a gift in 2007-2018.
Biographical Note
Eleanor Lansing Thomas "Elly" Elliott was a women's rights advocate who is best-known for successfully fighting Columbia University's attempt to take over Barnard College in the early 1970s. She served on the Barnard Board of Trustees for over 40 years beginning in 1959. She was President of the Board from 1973 to 1976. In the early 1950's, she served as the social secretary to the U.S. Secretary of State and her cousin, John Foster Dulles. In the 1970s she began serving on the board of directors of the Celanese Corporation. She was also a board member of the National Organization for Women's Legal Defense and Education Fund. In the 1980s, she served on the National Advisory Council on Women's Educational Programs. In the early 1990s, she was chairwoman of the Woodrow Wilson National Fellowship Foundation. She was a Life Trustee of New York-Presbyterian Hospital and a Life Overseer of Weill Cornell Medical College. She received an honorary doctorate of letters from Duke University in 2002 for her "advocacy for women in health and education." Her husband of 48 years, Jock Elliott, was a former chairman of the advertising firm Ogilvy and Mather.
Collection Overview
These papers consist of personal materials from the Elliott and Thomas families as well as administrative files from Elliott's work in various women's rights organizations and philanthropic activities.
The collection includes some material regarding Elly's husband, Jock Elliott, former chairman of the Ogilvy and Mather advertising firm. Included in the Thomas family materials is a series on Eleanor's mother, Dorothy Q. Thomas. In the legal and financial papers series, there are materials pertaining to the divorce and child support matters of Elliott's brother, James A. Thomas Jr.
The collection contains scrapbooks and photographs, as well as reel-to-reel audiotapes that require reformatting before use.
Related Material
Materials related to Elliott's husband, Jock, can be found in the Jock Elliott Papers. Materials related to Elliott's father, James A. Thomas, can be found in the James Augustus Thomas Papers.
Scrapbooks; Photographs; Women's health services -- New York (State) -- New York; Women in higher education -- New York (State) -- New York; Feminists -- New York (State) -- New York; Elliott, Jock; NOW Legal Defense and Education Fund; United States. Advisory Council on Women's Educational Programs; Barnard College -- History; Celanese Corporation; Elliott, Eleanor; Vogue (Paris, France); Barnard College -- Alumni and alumnae; Woodrow Wilson National Fellowship Foundation; Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture
- Dorothy Q. Thomas Series, 1768-2004, 7 boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  These materials document Eleanor Elliott's family of origin. Much of the material pertains to her mother, Dorothy Q. Thomas.
  Arrangement note
  Files are arranged by subject, and by alphabetical, then chronological arrangement within those subjects.
  - Correspondence - 1922-2004 and undated (Box 1)
  - Correspondence - Birth of Eleanor Elliott, 1926 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence - Death of James A. Thomas, 1940 (3 folders) (Box 1)
  - Correspondence - Death of Dorothy Q. Thomas, 1987-1988 (3 folders) (Box 1)
  - Estate papers - 1936-1988 (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - Estate papers - Thomas Family Genealogy, 1976-1977 (Box 2)
  - Estate papers - Dorothy Q. Thomas U/A Seventh of the Will, 1987 (Box 2)
  - Estate papers - Christie's Estate Sale, 1988 (4 folders) (Box 2)
  - Photos - 1920-1980 and undated (2 folders) (Box 3)
  - Scrapbooks and memorabilia - 1910-1958 (4 folders) (Box 3)
  - Scrapbooks and memorabilia - 1950-2000 and undated (3 folders) (Box 4)
  - Scrapbooks and memorabilia - John Foster Dulles Oral History Project, 1964-1966 (2 folders) (Box 4)
  - Scrapbooks and memorabilia - Death of Dorothy Q. Thomas, 1987 (Box 4)
  - Oversize - San Francisco Chronicle, April 18, 1906 and 1956 (2 folders) (Box 5)
  - Oversize - Photograph of Dorothy Q. Thomas at wedding of her daughter Eleanor Thomas and Jock Elliott, 1956 (Box 5)
  - Genealogical material, 1768-1972 and undated Dulles Oral History, 1956-1973 (Box 47)
  - Columbia University Oral History plus other writings and draft memoir (Box 48)
- Professional Series 1951-2005, 18 boxes
  This series contains material documenting Eleanor Elliott's work with various organizations as well as her philanthropic activity.
  This series is divided into three subseries: Correspondence, Research Files, and Writings and Speeches.
  - Professional Correspondence, 1951-2006
    - Board hassle, 1973 (Box 6)
    - Barnard correspondence, 1990-2006 (Box 6)
    - Barnard current, 1990-1992 (Box 6)
    - Foundation for Child Development correspondence, 2003-2006 (Box 6)
    - New York Hospital Correspondence, 1991-2006 (2 folders) (Box 6)
    - Woodrow Wilson Correspondence, 1994-2006 (2 folders) (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous professional correspondence, 1951-2003 (Box 7)
  - Research Files, 1971-2005
    - Altschul, Mr. Arthur G-Chairman, Board of Trustees-Barnard, 1977-1979 (Box 7)
    - Barnard College - Bill McGill, undated (Box 7)
    - Barnard College - Board of Trustees, 1974-1975 (Box 7)
    - Barnard College Board of Trustees, 2006 (Box 7)
    - Barnard College By-Laws, 1975-1977 (Box 7)
    - The Campaign for Barnard, 1993 (Box 7)
    - Barnard College Centennial, 1988-1989 (Box 7)
    - Barnard College Centennial, 1988-1989 (Box 8)
    - Development background material, 1966 (Box 8)
    - Development, 1970s-1990s (4 folders) (Box 8)
    - Eleanor Thomas Elliott Hall dedication, 1992 (3 folders) (Box 8)
    - Barnard College - Eleanor Thomas Elliott Scholarship recipients, 1999 (Box 8)
    - Barnard College Executive Committee, 1976-1977 (Box 9)
    - Feminism, 1969 (Box 9)
    - Finance salaries, 1975-1976 (Box 9)
    - Funds and grants, 1976-1978 (Box 9)
    - Fund raising, 1971 (Box 9)
    - Long range planning, 1969-1976 (Box 9)
    - Miscellaneous, 1975-1976 (Box 9)
    - Missions and goals, 1976 (Box 9)
    - Nominating committee, 1974-1979 (3 folders) (Box 9)
    - Inauguration of President Mattfield, 1976 (Box 9)
    - President Jacqueline A. Mattfield, 1976-1981 (Box 9)
    - Barnard College - Operational budget, 1975-1977 (2 folders) (Box 10)
    - Barnard College personnel, 1975-1978 (Box 10)
    - Barnard College reunions and anniversaries, 1993-2002 (Box 10)
    - Barnard residence halls, 1988-2002 (Box 10)
    - Barnard Presidential search committee, 1975-1980 (Box 10)
    - Barnard College Student Affairs Committee, 1975-1976 (Box 10)
    - Barnard College students, 1975-1979 (Box 10)
    - Barnard College talks, 1976 (Box 10)
    - Barnard College Women's Center background, 1970-1971 (Box 10)
    - Barnard-Columbia relations, 1970s (7 folders) (Box 11)
    - Barnard-Columbia relations, 1970s-1990s (Box 12)
    - Celanese reports, 1974-1985 (3 folders) (Box 12)
    - Duke visit, 2002 (Box 12)
    - Feminism, 1970-1983 (3 folders) (Box 12)
    - Feminism, 1976-1983 (Box 13)
    - Foundation for Child Development - Brim, Dr. Orville G., Jr., 1977-1980 (Box 13)
    - Grant FDN matter, 1978-1979 (Box 13)
    - Miscellaneous, 1975-1978 (Box 13)
    - National survey, 1976-1977 (Box 13)
    - Personal manual, 1977-1981 (Box 13)
    - Chronological files, 1995-1999 (3 folders) (Box 13)
    - Helen Reid biography, 1990-1993 (Box 13)
    - John Foster Dulles, undated (Box 13)
    - Miscellaneous, 1968-2006 (2 folders) (Box 14)
    - NACWEP correspondence, 1982-1983 (Box 14)
    - New York Hospital Bylaws, 1953-1971 (Box 14)
    - Cornell Union Joint Agreement, 1977 (Box 14)
    - Files, 1987 (Box 14)
    - New York State Republican Women Legislators Action Network, 1979 (Box 14)
    - NOW/Feminism, 1984-1987 (2 folders) (Box 14)
    - Saint Margaret's Chapel Project, 1980-2006 (Box 14)
    - Scudder, Stevens and Clark Correspondence, 1975-1979 (Box 14)
    - Sulzberger biography, 1992-1993 (Box 14)
    - United Way of New York City, 1992-1993 (Box 14)
    - Women in business, 1976-2005 and undated (Box 15)
    - Women's Health Symposium, 1987-1995 (3 folders) (Box 15)
    - Woodrow Wilson National Fellowship Foundation, 1982-1990 (Box 15)
    - Woodrow Wilson Foundation, 1991-1994 (3 folders) (Box 15)
    - Woodrow Wilson Foundation, 1991-2002 (Box 16-18)
    - Woodrow Wilson Foundation, 1998-1999 (Box 19)
    - Woodrow Wilson Foundation 50th anniversary, 1995 (Box 19)
    - Woodrow Wilson Foundation visiting fellows, 1983-1984 (Box 19)
    - Zissner, 1998-1999 (Box 19)
    - Barnard College, 1973-1998 (Box 49)
    - Celanese Corporation, 1974-1976 (Box 49)
    - CIT Directorships, 1978 (Box 50)
    - Duke Honors, 2002 (Box 50)
    - Foundation for Child Development, 1979-2004 (Box 50)
    - National Advisory Council on Women's Educational Programs, 1981-1984 (Box 50)
    - New York Hospital, 1982-1994 (Box 51)
    - NOW Legal Defense and Education Fund, 1990 (Box 51)
    - Oggi Magazine, September 1953 (Box 51)
    - V.S. Marines, 2004-2005 (Box 51)
    - Chronological files, 1973-2005 (3 folders) (Box 51)
    - Chronological files, 2002-2005 (Box 52)
    - Writings and Speeches, 1953-2006 (Box 52)
      Eleanor Elliott's writings consist of published pieces in Glamour, Vogue, Town and Country and by the Feminist Press. They also include files from an unpublished memoir. Speeches were given at the following institutions and events, among others: The National Conference of Christians and Jews, The National Association of Fund Raising Executives, Colony Club, New York Association for the Blind, Columbia Graduate School of Business, International House of New York, Women's Forum Meeting, Forum for Women Directors, New York Junior League, Planned Giving Group of New York, Center for the Study of Philanthropy, Women and Money Conference, New York Hospital, St. Nicholas Society, United Hospital Fund, Women's Health Symposium, Meeting of Women and Foundations-Corporate Philanthropy; Celanese Forum for Women Directors.
    - Elly writing, 1953-2003 (Box 19)
    - Glamour, April 1960 and Vogue, September 1961 (Box 19)
    - Vogue, June 1973 and Town and Country, 1975 (Box 19)
    - Speech notebook, undated (Box 19)
    - Barnard College, 1970s (Box 20)
    - Speeches, 1971-1985 (5 folders) (Box 20)
    - Memoir files, 1934-2006 and undated (6 folders) (Box 21)
    - Speeches by others, 1971-1979 (Box 21)
    - Speeches, 1977-2006 (Box 22-23, 52)
- Scrapbook Series, 1851-1978, 21 boxes
  Bound scrapbooks are arranged in original order, with original numbering noted in Roman Numerals by their creators. Scrapbooks missing from the Roman Numeral sequence were not received as part of this collection. Loose materials intended to be mounted in the scrapbooks is included in Box 37. Materials include clippings, photographs, correspondence, programs and miscellaneous printed items.
  - Scrapbook I - Eleanor Elliott, 1944-1950 (Box 24)
  - Scrapbook II - Thomas Family, 1923-1928; Scrapbook X - Read Family clippings, 1851-1892 (Box 25)
  - Scrapbook IV - Eleanor Elliott, 1932-1941 (Box 26)
  - Scrapbook V - James A. Thomas, 1890-1920 (Box 27)
  - Scrapbook VI - James A. Thomas, 1930-1939 (Box 27A)
  - Scrapbook VII - James A. Thomas, 1890-1920 (Box 28)
  - Scrapbook XI - Eleanor and Jock Elliott, 1956-1959 (Box 29)
  - Scrapbook XIV - James A. Thomas, 1930-1938, including dedication of Duke University's Thomas Room; Scrapbook XXIV - Eleanor Elliott, 1956-1978 (Box 30)
  - Scrapbook XVI - James A. Thomas, 1920-1929 (Box 31)
  - Scrapbook XVII - Eleanor Elliott, 1951-1952 (Box 32)
  - Scrapbook XX - Eleanor Elliott, 1948-1956 (Box 33)
  - Scrapbook XXII - Eleanor Elliott, Washington, D.C., 1953 (Box 34)
  - Scrapbook XXVIII - Eleanor Elliott, 1958-1960 (Box 35)
  - Scrapbook XXVIII - Eleanor Elliott, debut year, 1943-1944 (Box 36)
  - Scrapbook documenting Duke University's Thomas Room, 1942 (Box 37)
  - Loose materials, 1940-1941 (Box 37)
  - Loose materials from Scrapbook I, 1941-1948 (Box 37)
  - Loose materials, 1949-1965 (2 folders) (Box 37)
  - Clippings, 1973-1997 (Box 37)
  - Photographs of young Eleanor Elliott, undated (Box 37)
  - Scrapbook IX - Snapshots and portraits, 1920s-1940s (Box 41)
  - Scrapbook XI - 1890s-1900s, James A. Thomas, Sr. tobacco (Box 42)
  - Scrapbook XII - Dorothy Q. Thomas (Box 43)
  - Scrapbook XIII - James A. Thomas, Sr., 1920s-1930s (Box 44)
  - Scrapbook XXV - Jock and Eleanor wedding album, 1956 (Box 45)
  - Jock Elliott tribute scrapbook (Box 46)
- Legal and Financial Series, 1920-2006; 5 boxes
  Legal and Financial papers of the Elliott and Thomas families including estate papers, wills, appraisals of property, and legal correspondence regarding the estates of the two families.
  Also included are the legal and financial documents and correspondence pertaining to the divorce, custody, and child support matters of Elliott's brother, James A. Thomas Jr. and his wife Anne Macdonald Thomas.
  - Legal and financial papers, 1920-2006 (Box 53-56)
  - James A. Thomas, Jr. divorce and child support proceedings, 1963-1976 (Box 93)
- Memorabilia Series, 1960-2006; 14 boxes
  - Memorabilia and ephemera (Box 39)
  - Memorabilia and ephemera from various family events, travel itineraries and journals, and articles about Eleanor Elliott and Jock Elliott, among other items (Box 57-66)
  - New York Hospital Life Governor Award, 1996 (Box 87)
  - Recipes (Box 88)
  - Jock Elliott memorabilia from Apollo 11 launch (Box 89)
- Correspondence Series, 1922-2007 and undated; 14 boxes
  Correspondence is divided into four subseries: Personal, Jock and Eleanor Elliott, Family, and Funeral and Sympathy. Within these subseries, correspondence is arranged in rough chronological order, unless otherwise specified.
  - Personal Correspondence, 1935-2006 and undated
    Noted correspondents include Richard Rogers, David Ogilvy and Louis Auchincloss.
    - 1935-1970s (9 folders) (Box 67)
    - 1974-2006 (9 folders) (Box 68)
    - Eleanor Elliott's 75th birthday, 2001 (5 folders) (Box 69)
  - Correspondence between Jock and Eleanor Elliott
    - Correspondence between Eleanor and Jock Elliott, June-July 1956 (Box 40)
    - Wedding correspondence, 1956 (Box 40)
    - Assorted correspondence, 1988-2004 and undated (Box 40)
    - Correspondence between Jock and Elly, 1948-1989 and undated (5 folders) (Box 70)
    - Correspondence between Jock and Elly, 1950-2005 and undated (6 folders) (Box 71)
    - Jock and Elly's 10th and 30th anniversary correspondence and photos (6 folders) (Box 72)
    - Correspondence to Jock Elliott from Elly, 1949-2005 and undated (Box 73)
    - Letters between Jock and Eleanor Elliott, 1956-2005 and undated (Box 73)
  - Family Correspondence, 1951-1995
    - Letters from Germany, France and England, 1951 (Box 38)
    - Eleanor and Jock Elliott's letters from Italy, 1958 (Box 38)
    - Assorted personal correspondence, 1951-1993 (Box 38)
    - Family correspondence, 1980-1995 (3 folders) (Box 38)
    - Thomas Family - James A. Thomas, Jr., 1937-1970s (Box 74)
    - Thomas Family, 1940-2007 and undated (2 folders) (Box 74)
    - Thomas Family, Eleanor F. Lansing to Dorothy Q. Thomas, 1922-1933 (3 folders) (Box 74)
  - Funeral and Sympathy Correspondence, 2000-2006
    Includes correspondence to Eleanor Elliott's family after her death, as well as correspondence written to Eleanor Elliott after the passing of her husband, Jock and her brother, James A. Thomas, Jr.
    - 2006-2007 (4 folders) (Box 75)
    - Funeral programs and memorabilia, 2006 (2 folders) (Box 76)
    - Funeral planning, 2006 (Box 76)
    - Jock Elliott funeral and sympathy, 2005 (Box 76)
    - James A. Thomas, Jr. funeral and sympathy, 2000 (Box 76)
    - Jock Elliott condolences, A-H (8 folders) (Box 76)
    - Jock Elliott condolences, I-W (12 folders) (Box 77)
    - Jock Elliott condolences, X-Z (Box 78)
- Photographs series, 1870-2007; 10 boxes, 1 folder
  Photographs are arranged in rough chronological order unless otherwise indicated.
  - 1870-1950s (4 folders) (Box 78)
  - 1950s (Box 79)
  - Jock and Eleanor Elliott wedding photos, London, 1956 (Box 79)
  - 1960s (Box 79)
  - 1970s (Box 79)
  - 1980s and 1990s and undated (Box 80)
  - 1984-1985 (Box 80)
  - Dedication of Staffa, 1986 (Box 80)
  - 1990s and undated (Box 80)
  - 1992 (Box 80)
  - 2000s and undated (Box 81)
  - 75th birthday party, Saint Regis Hotel, NYC, April 26, 2001 (2 folders) (Box 81)
  - Portraits, 1930s-1990s (3 folders) (Box 81)
  - Misc. photos (Box 82)
  - Images from Christmas book, undated (Box 82)
  - Photo negatives (Box 82)
  - Elly and Jock photo album (Box 82)
  - 2000s photo album (Box 82)
  - Remembering Elly - February 28, 2007, Barnard College (Box 82)
  - Celebrating the birth of Eleanor Lansing Thomas (Box 82)
  - 1980s and 1990s snapshots (Box 83-84)
  - 2000s snapshots (Box 85)
  - Photo album of Jock and Eleanor in Kinlochan, Scotland (Box 85)
  - Elly, c. 1960 (Box 87)
  - Oversize photos, 1930s-2000s (Box 90)
  - Oversize photos (Oversize-folder 1)
- Audiovisual Materials Series,1964-2007, 1 box
  - Reel to reel tapes, c. 1964 containing interviews with various family members (Box 86)
  - DVD - Lifetime achievement award presented to Elly and Jock at the 2007 New York Red Cross Ball (Box 86)
  - DVD - Foundation for Child Development Annual Dinner, 2007 (Box 86)
- Barnard College Series, 1974-2000
  Access Restrictions
  This series is closed to research until 2025.
  - Papers regarding the resignation of Martha Peterson, Barnard College President, 1975 (Box 91)
  - Barnard College Board of Trustees, 1974-1975 (Box 91)
  - Census of Barnard College Alumnae, 1962 (Box 91)
  - Blanche Graubard correspondence, 1975-2000 (Box 91)
  - Statistical profile of Barnard College faculty, 1974 (Box 91)
  - Absorption of Barnard by Columbia, 1975-1976 (Box 91)
  - Correspondence regarding new Barnard president, 1975 (Box 91)
  - Marstellar/Plimpton correspondence, 1975 (Box 91)
  - Memos, correspondence, 1978-1981 (Box 92)
  - Evaluation of Barnard College for the Middle States Association - March 6-9, 1960 (Box 92)
  - Barnard's New Chapter: A Three-Year Report (Box 92)
  - Faculty Letters - 1975 (Box 92)
  - Resignation of Martha Peterson, Barnard College President - 1975 (Box 92)
  - Notebook Diary Entry - July 25, 1975 (Box 92)